Preliminary Inventory to the Roger A. Freeman Papers, 1950-1990
Hoover Institution Archives
- PUBLIC SCHOOL FINANCE
  - Resources for schools - General review
    - Local sources
      - Property tax (general considerations)
        - History and tax burden
          - Property tax burden (Box 220-221)
            - total by states and localities
            - residential
            - utility property
            - other industrial and commercial
            - farm property
        - Property tax limitations (Box 221)
          - Tax rates
          - Bonding
          - Exemptions
          - Relief - circuit breakers
        - Assessment administration (Box 222)
          - Fractional assessment ratios and ratio studies
          - Legal provision
          - Court decisions
          - Uniformity and administrative competence
        - Personal property - assessment and tax burden
        - Land taxation and classification
        - Efforts at assessment equalization
          - State
          - Local
        - Case studies of tax rate elections (Box 223)
        - Property tax improvement (Can the property tax be made more productive?)
      - Non-property taxes (Box 224)
        - Local non-property taxes
        - Municipalities
        - Schools
      - School Debts
        - Debt limitations and margins
        - Bond elections, successes and failures (Box 225)
        - Local authorities and other methods of circumventing debt restrictions
    - State school aid
      - History of state responsibility and support
      - State control of schools
      - Extent of state aid, total and by states
      - Forms (programs) of state aid (by states), flat or equalized, for operation
      - For construction, grants, loans, authorities, other assistance
      - State equalization programs, measures of need, property valuations (adjusted or not), indices, Serrano case and sequel (Box 225-226)
      - Schools in the state finance picture, revenues, other costs, assets (Box 227)
      - State fiscal capacity, total effort by states
    - Federal aid to education
      - History of federal activities in education (Box 227-228)
      - History of movement for federal aid to schools to 1949 (Box 228)
      - History of movement for federal aid to schools since 1949
      - Case for federal aid (Box 229)
      - Case against federal aid (Box 229-230)
      - Material from organizations against federal aid
        - U.S. Chamber of Commerce and NAM
        - Others and individuals (Box 231-232)
      - Material from organizations for federal aid (Box 232-233)
        - National Education Association
        - Others and individuals (Box 233)
        - Committee for Economic Development
      - Material from official commissions
        - Prior to 1953
        - Commission on Intergovernmental Relations
        - State Conferences on Education (Box 234)
        - White House Conference on Education, 1955
        - White House Conference on Education, 1965
        - President's School Finance Commission, 1970-72
        - ACIR
      - Congressional hearing, reports and debates (Box 235)
      - Proposals on school aid in recent years (since 1950) (Box 236)
      - Forces, motivations, pro and con
      - Proposals for federal aid, 1958-1966 (Box 236-239)
      - Conclusions on federal aid
        - Need for
        - Prospects
        - Building considerations
- O.H.S. (Order of the Holy Sepulchre of Jerusalem)
  - General rules and materials
  - General rules and materials (Box 240)
  - Other
  - Beltritti, James Joseph
  - Cazzaniga, Giovanni (Rome)
  - Campagno, Vincent I.
  - Courtright, Hernando
  - Craig, John J., GCHS
  - Folsom, Frank M., KGCHS (Box 241)
  - Hickel, Walter J.
  - Hurley, Mark J.
  - Lambert, L. George
  - McGucken, Joseph T.
  - McIntyre, Cardinal
  - McNeany, Joseph
  - McElligott, Edward R.
  - Maggio, Albert E.
  - Maher, Leo T.
  - Miller, Jo Zach, III
  - Rizzi, Nicolo (Geneva)
  - Rogers, G.M.
  - Ryan, Joseph T.
  - Tisserant, Eugene Caridnal
  - Western Delegation
  - Agriculture (Box 242)
  - Budget, U.S.
    - General
    - Defense (A) (Box 243)
  - Communications and highways
  - Economics in general, 1962-68
  - Economics in general, 1949-1961 (Box 244)
  - Foreign trade and tariffs
  - Foreign trade and tariffs (Box 245)
  - Housing
    - 1964-66
    - -1963 (Box 246)
  - Inflation
  - Political science
  - Religion
  - Republican Program
  - Republican Program/ Republican National Committee (Box 247)
- HIGHER EDUCATION FILE (Box 247-248)
  - General
  - Enrollment - job market (Box 249-250)
  - Facilities (Box 250-251)
  - Faculty (Box 251-252)
  - Curriculum and quality (Box 252)
  - Finances in general (Box 253-254)
  - Tuitions and fees (Box 254)
  - Donations (Box 255)
  - State and local government support (Box 255-256)
  - Federal activities in higher education (Box 256-257)
  - Federal research aid (Box 257-258)
  - Federal grants (Box 258)
  - Federal control issue (Box 259)
  - Church-state issue (constitutional, etc.)
  - Student aid (scholarships, loans, work-study, etc.) (Box 259-263)
  - Tax relief (Box 264)
    - Deductions, exemptions, flat percentage credits
    - Sliding scale tax credits (Box 264-265)
  - Medical schools (Box 265)
  - Engineering and science
  - Student unrest (Box 266)
    - General
    - Causes of disturbances
    - Student demands (Box 267)
    - Organizational tactics
    - Faculty and administration response
    - Governmental response
    - Public opinion
    - Consequences of disturbances
    - Descriptions of disturbances
    - High school unrest
  - Other
  - Supply and demand
  - Place and scope of education, to 1959 (Box 268-269)
  - Population and enrollment, to 1962
  - Effort for education, to 1962
  - Total school personnel, to 1962 (Box 270)
  - Teacher util., to 1961
  - TV and movies, to 1962 (Box 271)
  - Curriculum, to 1960 (Box 271-273)
- "WHAT MAKES IVAN RUN?"
  - Materials and first drafts (Box 273)
  - Books
  - Preface
  - Chapters
    - I (Box 274)
    - II
    - III
    - IV (Box 275)
    - V
    - VI (Box 276)
    - VII
    - VIII
    - IX
    - X
  - Trip notes
  - USSR trip, 1964
    - Film problems
    - Trip plans (cosmos, etc.)
    - Publicity
    - Kabul-Tashkent flight (Box 277)
    - Speeches on trip
- White House Conference on Education, 1955 (Box 277-278)
- U.S. Office of Education, "Public School Finance Programs of the U.S.," controversy (Box 278)
- Committee of Four
  - Drafts and reports
  - Final reports
- White House Conference of Education (Box 278-279)
  - General
  - Finance - staff papers
- Education - by states
  - Alabama (Box 279)
  - Alaska
  - Arizona
  - Arkansas
  - California (Box 280)
    - General
    - Miscellaneous
    - Takes
    - Education
      - 1964-65
      - 1961-63
      - 1958 (and prior) - 1960 (Box 281)
  - Colorado
  - Connecticut
  - Delaware
  - District of Columbia (Box 282)
  - Florida
  - Georgia
  - Hawaii
  - Idaho
  - Illinois
  - Indiana (Box 283)
  - Iowa
  - Kansas
  - Kentucky
  - Louisiana
  - Maine
  - Maryland
  - Massachusetts
  - Michigan (Box 284)
  - Minnesota
  - Mississippi
  - Missouri
  - Montana
  - Nebraska
  - Nevada
  - New Hampshire
  - New Jersey
  - New Mexico
  - New York (Box 285)
    - General
    - 1961-on to 1960
    - to 1960
  - North Carolina (Box 286)
  - North Dakota
  - Ohio
  - Oklahoma
  - Oregon
  - Pennsylvania
  - Rhode Island
  - South Carolina
  - South Dakota (Box 287)
  - Tennessee
  - Texas
  - Utah
    - 1964
    - 1960-63 (Box 288)
    - prior to 1960
  - Vermont
  - Virginia
  - Washington
  - West Virginia (Box 289)
  - Wisconsin
  - Wyoming
  - Other countries
- Correspondence, 1971-73
  - A (Box 290)
  - Advisory Commission on Intergovernmental Relations
  - American Enterprise Institute
  - American Security Council
  - Applications
  - B
  - Baroody, William J., Jr.
  - Baroody, William J., Sr.
  - Boberg, Anna
  - C
  - Census Advisory Committee on Privacy and Confidentiality (Box 291)
    - General
    - Washington, D.C., September 1973
  - Citizens for Educational Freedom
  - D
  - Donner Foundation
  - E
  - F
  - G
  - Glenn, Thomas L.
  - Governmental Research Association (Box 292)
  - Griffen, Joy
  - H
  - Campbell, W. Glenn
  - Campbell, Rita R.
  - Board of Overseers meeting, Hoover Institution
    - July 21, 1972
    - July 19, 1973
  - Hoover Institution Research Program in the 1970s
  - Hoover Centennial lectures
  - Inter-collegiate Studies Institute, Inc.
  - J
  - K
  - L
  - Library Bulletin
  - Mc
  - M (Box 293)
  - Miscellaneous
  - 25th Anniversary Meeting, the Mont Pelerin Society, Montreux, Switzerland, September 3-9, 1972
  - N
  - National Industrial Conference Board
  - National Tax Association, Tax Institute of America
  - National Tax Association, Committee on Intergovernmental Fiscal Relations
  - O
  - P-Q
  - Philadelphia Society
  - R
  - S
  - Sanders, Maryelinor
  - Shockley, William B.
  - Stanford University (Box 294)
  - T
  - U
  - V
  - William Volker Fund
  - W
  - Wall Street Journal
  - Wilkinson, Ernest L.
  - X-Y-Z
- Higher education
  - General
  - Faculty (Box 295)
  - Finances
  - Federal activities
  - Federal grants (Box 296-297)
  - Student aid
  - Tax relief
  - Medical schools
  - Engineering and science
- Speeches and articles, 4/62 - 10/63
  - The Catholic World and the Catholic Reporter, Big Government and the Moral Order, May 1962 (Box 298)
  - The Graduate Journal (Texas), Aid to Higher Education, 1962
  - Book Review - Journal of Finance, Rivlin's "Role of Government in Financing Higher Education," June 1962
  - Mt. St. Mary's College Panel Discussion, 7/18/62
  - Speech, Rotary Club, West Los Angeles, 7/19/62
  - Public Works, preliminary drafts
  - National Legislative Service Conference, Phoenix, September 21, 1962 (Box 299)
  - Letter re: ADC paper at Phoenix
  - Public Works, final draft and correspondence
  - Center for Strategic Studies Conference, 1/25/63 (Box 300)
    - Work paper, statistics, drafts
    - Correspondence and final text
    - Priorities - W.G.C.
  - Analysis of Education Message, Senator Dirksen, February 1963
  - Analysis of Aid to Education, Representative Taft, 3/14/63
  - Tax Cuts or Tax Reform, AEI, 3/63
  - Economic Priorities (Conservative Papers), May 1963 (Box 301)
  - Senate Testimony
    - May 1963, correspondence
    - May 27, 1963
  - University of Wisconsin Seminar, June 10-22, 1963 (Box 302)
  - Tax Credits, AEI Booklet, September 1963
  - Senior Colloquium, Autumn 1963, SC13, Tax Reform and Expenditure Policy
  - Los Altos Republican Women, 10/14/63
  - Speech, League of California Cities, SF, CA, October 22, 1963
- Speeches and articles, 1951 - 7/1958
  - Fact and Fiction on Washington State's Tax Burden, February 1953 (Box 303)
  - The Controller's Responsibility in Public Affairs, December 1952
  - Your Dollar's Worth of State Government, June 1952
  - State and Local Tax Burden in 48 States
    - January 1953
    - Answers from other states on tax figues and fiscal data for S and L tax table
  - What Price State Government? Reporting to the Taxpayers, March 1953
  - How Can Voters Understand?, September 1953 (Box 304)
  - State Aid and Support of Our Public Schools, State Government, 10/1953
  - State Aid and Support of Public Schools, October 1953
  - The Future of State-Local Relations, November 1953
  - How Fast Will State and Local Government Spending Rise?, 2/1954
  - Can the State Budget Be Balanced?, April 1954
  - A Hundred Billion in State and Local Public Works, May 1954
  - Outlook for State Governments, 8/54 (Box 305)
  - Our Federal System at the Crossroads
    - 11/54
    - Vital speeches, 3-15-55
  - State and Local Tax Burden, February 1955
  - Hearing Before House Education Committee, Washington, D.C., April 26, 1955
  - Federal Aid to School Construction, April 1955
  - The Property Tax - Bulwark of Local Government, July 1955
  - American Enterprise Association, November 1955
  - "Federal Aid to Education Boon or Bane"
  - Government's Role in Education, White House Conference, November 1955 (Box 306)
  - Tax Journal, March & June 1956, Crisis in School Finance I & II
  - Public Affairs Research Council of Louisiana, March 9, 1956, "Shifting Pattern of Responsibility"
  - School and Society, March 17, 1956, "A New Look at Federal Aid to Education"
  - GRA Reporter, 3156, "Grass Roots Wither at Education Meeting"
  - Utah Foundation, May 10, 1956
  - Civil Federation, Chicago, "Dollars and Sense in Education," October 31, 1956
  - National Municipal League, Memphis, Tennessee, November 11-12, 1956
  - Association of American Physicians and Surgeons, April 26, 1957, "Federal Aid to Education Boon or Bane" (Box 307)
  - Education Section, "Federal Expense Policy for Health, Education, Social Security," WGC at JEC panel
  - Governmental Research Association, Chicago, September 25, 1957, "Are We Shortchanging the Schools?"
  - Illinois State Chamber of Commerce, 10/18/57, "How Illinois Measures Up in Meeting Its Sch. Pro."
  - Public Works - Fond Hope and Harsh Realities, November 1957
  - Joint Economic Committee of Congress, "Public Works - Fond Hope and Harsh Realities," November 1957
  - Bolivia: A Case Study in Foreign Aid, December 1957
  - Gwinn Study, Congressional Record, 1/15/58
  - Talk, New Mexico Taxpayers Association, Santa Fe, New Mexico, April 2, 1958
  - "Are the American People Starving Their Schools?" July 1958
- Speeches and articles, August 1958-1960
  - School Needs and State Finance, SF, August 11, 1958, Nasbo, 19th annual meeting (Box 308)
  - Rough Weather Ahead for State Finances and School Support, 9/18/58, National Legislative Conference
  - GRA Meeting, 10/6/-8/58, Shawnee on Delaware
  - Speech before the National Legislative Conference, Boston, MA, 9/18/58
  - Talk to D.C. Republicans, 11/6/58 (Box 309)
  - GRA Meeting, 10/6-8/58
  - Arden House Conference, November 11, 1958
  - Annual Meeting of the Iowa Taxpayers Association, 12/1/58, Des Moines, Iowa
  - Farm Bureau Federation, December 8, 1958
  - Excerpts from Reviews and Comments on "School Needs in the Decade Ahead," 1958
  - National School Boards Association Conference, January 25-28, 1959, SF, CA
  - Federal Aid to Education, February 1959 (Box 310)
  - Parade article, May 10, 1959 (Box 311)
  - Roger Freeman Answers NEA, April-May 1959
  - "How Shall We Pay For the Schools?" American Farm Bureau Federation, Columbus, Ohio, June 30, 1959
  - Unmet Needs in Education for W.M. Volker Fund, July 1959
  - Speech, "Community Leadership Seminar of Fels Institute and Greater Philadelphia Movement," 12/16/59
  - Federal Aid to Education, 1960 (Box 312)
  - Speech, Governmental Research Association, St. Louis, October 3, 1960
  - National Municipal League, Phoenix, Arizona, November 13-16, 1960 (Box 313)
- Speeches and articles, 1961 - 3/1962
  - NTA Committee on Financing, Education-Report, January 1961
  - Senate Republican Policy Committee
  - Article for "Nation's Business", 1/31/61, AEA, Bill Analysis
  - Speech, Archdiocesan Council of Catholic Women, March 10, 1961 (Box 314)
  - Testimony before Senate, March 13, 1961
  - Speech, Brookings Institute, Cottage Grove, Eugene, Oregon, March 16, 1961
  - Press conference, 3/27/61
  - Article for Nation's Business, March 28, 1961
  - Speech, Methodists Men's Meeting, Alhambra, April 25, 1961
  - CMC Parents' Day, "Federal Aid to Education," 4/22/61
  - Kiwanis Club, Ontario, April 28, 1961
  - Chamber of Commerce speech, Los Angeles, May 4, 1961
  - Claremont Republican Club, May 11, 1961
  - Monrovia Women's Club, May 11, 1961
  - Municipal Finance Officers Association, Seattle, Washington, May 21-25, 1961 (Box 315)
  - Wall Street Journal "Private Enterprise Beats Government Planning in Asia," June 19, 1961
  - House Republican Policy Committee Education Study, June 29, 1961
  - Los Angeles CoC Federal Affairs Committee, Alhambra Kiwanis, July 24 & 26
  - Claremont Men's College Tax Seminar (Box 315-316)
  - Debate Manual, September 1961 (Box 316)
  - Senate Committee Welfare, September 12, 1961
  - Western Governmental Research Association Conference, Berkeley, September 28-29, 1961 (Box 317)
  - Princeton Alumni Weekly, 9/29/61
  - County Supervisors Association of California, San Francisco, October 4-6, 1961
  - California County Welfare Directors Association, November 16, 1961
  - The Catholic World, Tax Credits, January 1962 (Box 318)
  - Brookings Rehabilitation Conference, Santa Barbara, 2/5/62
  - Ave Maria, School Aid Debate, March 1962
  - Graduate Symposium, Dallas, March 19, 1962
  - School Busing (Box 319-321)
  - Miscellaneous
- Commission on Intergovernmental Relations (Box 322-325)
- Correspondence, 1957-1960
  - A (Box 325)
  - American Farm Bureau Federation
  - Aloras, Pilar
  - B
  - Bans, Herbert
  - Beckett, John A.
  - Burrell's
  - C
  - Claremont Men's College
  - Commission on National Goals
  - D (Box 326)
  - F
  - Freeman, Roger (personal)
  - Furman, James M., Jr.
  - G
  - Gwinn, Ralph W.
  - H
  - I
  - Institute for Social Science Research
  - J
  - K
  - L
  - Los Angeles Chamber of Commerce (Box 327)
  - M
  - Moley, Raymond
  - N
  - National Municipal League
  - O
  - P
  - Q
  - R
  - S (Box 328)
  - T
  - U
  - V
  - Volker (William) Fund
  - W
  - XYZ
  - Old letters
  - Filled requisitions, 1960
- Correspondence, 1961-63
  - A (Box 329)
  - Advisory Commission on Intergovernmental Relations (from 1957)
  - America
  - B
  - Bernstein, Michael J.
  - Bingham, Jo
  - Blum, Rev. Virgil (Box 330)
  - Boarman, Patrick M.
  - Bureau of the Census
  - C
  - Cowling, Donald J.
  - Curtis, Thomas B.
  - D
  - E
  - F
  - Foundation for Voluntary Welfare
  - G
  - Goldwater, Barry
  - Governmental Research Association, Inc.
  - H (Box 331)
  - Howard, John A.
  - I
  - Institute for Social Research
  - J
  - K
  - L
  - Los Angeles Chamber of Commerce
  - M
  - McGucken, Archbishop
  - McIntyre, Cardinal
  - Moley, Raymond
  - N
  - National Association of Tax Administrators
  - National Municipal League
  - National Tax Association (Box 332)
  - O
  - P
  - Q
  - R
  - Relm Foundation
  - Research and Publications Committee (Hoover)
  - Requisitions (Box 333)
  - S
  - Stanford University
  - T
  - Tax Institute
  - U
  - V
  - W
  - Wall Street Journal (Box 334)
  - Wilkinson, Ernest L.
  - XYZ
- Correspondence, 1964-67
  - A
  - Advisory Commission on Intergovernmental Relations
  - Alchian, Arline
  - American Enterprise Institute
  - Applications for assistant
  - Arlington House Publishers
  - B
  - Baroody, William J., Jr.
  - Bernstein, Michael J.
  - Birkin, D.
  - Blum, Rev. Virgil
  - Boarman, Patrick M. (Box 335)
  - Bolling, Landrum R.
  - Brock, Bill
  - Byers, William
  - Center for American Studies
  - Chamber of Commerce of the U.S.
  - Citizens National Committee for Higher Education
  - Cornuelle, Richard
  - Curtis, Thomas B.
  - D
  - Dirksen, Everett M.
  - E
  - F
  - Foundation for Voluntary Welfare
  - Fry, Brian
  - G
  - Goldwater, Barry (Box 336)
  - Governmental esearch Association, Inc.
  - H
  - Haldane
  - Healy, Patrick
  - Hoover Institution
  - Hurley, Francis T.
  - I
  - J
  - K
  - Kennedy Institute of Politics (Harvard)
  - Kirwan, J.R.
  - Kuehnelt-Leddihn, Erik R., von
  - L
  - Lincoln Foundation (Box 337)
  - M
  - McCormick, Robert L.
  - McGucken, Archbishop
  - N
  - National Review
  - National Tax Association
  - National Tax Association (Box 338)
  - O
  - Olin Foundation, Inc. (Charles L. Horn)
  - P
  - Phalanx
  - Philadelphia Society, The
  - Q
  - R
  - Relm Foundation
  - Research and Publications Committee (Hoover)
  - Ribicoff, Senator Abraham
  - Romney, George
  - S (Box 339)
  - Shockley, William B.
  - Stanford University
  - Stanford Faculty Club
  - Stans, Maurice
  - T
  - Tax Institute
  - Time: Touche, Ross, Bailey & Smart
  - U
  - U.S. government (various departments)
  - V
  - Volker Fund
  - W (Box 340)
  - Wall Street Journal
  - War Colleges budgets
  - War On Poverty
  - Wilkinson, Ernest L.
  - XYZ
- Correspondence, 1968-1970
  - A
  - Advisory Commission on Intergovernmental Relations
  - Allen, Richard
  - Applications for assistant
  - Applications for assistant (Box 341)
  - B
  - Baroody, William J.
  - C
  - D
  - E
  - F
  - Fry, Brian
  - G
  - Governmental Research Association
  - H (Box 342)
  - Hoover Institution
  - I
  - Intercollegiate Studies Institute, Inc.
  - J
  - K
  - L
  - M
  - Mc (Box 343)
  - Manis, Rod
  - Miscellaneous
  - Moley, Raymond
  - N
  - National Tax Association
  - Nixon, Richard M.
  - O
  - P-Q
  - Philadelphia Society, The
  - Parents Rights, Inc.
  - R
  - Republican Research Reports
  - R.O.T.C., 1969
  - S
  - Shockley, William B.
  - Stanford University (Box 344)
  - Stanford Republican Club
  - T
  - Tax Institute of America
  - U
  - V
  - Wilkinson, Ernest L.
  - Wyden, Edith
  - XYZ
- National Tax Association (Box 345)
  - General
  - J.L. Ruether
  - Correspondence
  - Committee on the Financing of Public Education (Box 346)
  - Conference, 1959
  - Public education (Box 347)
  - Membership lists, notes on meetings, progress reports (Box 348)
  - Lists, drafts, letters, etc.
- Bolivia, 1951-57
- Bolivia, 1951-57 (Box 349-350)
- Office of Governor of Washington
  - 1950-56 (Box 351-353)
  - 1953-56 (Box 353-359)
- Property Tax (Box 359-361)
- Public Works, 1954-1963 (Box 362-363)
- Republican Program, 1963-64 (Box 364)
- "School Needs in the Decade Ahead" (Box 365-373)
- Taxes for schools (Box 374-376)
- Welfare by states (Box 376-381)
- White House files, 1969-1970 (Box 381-383)
- Unprocessed (Box 384-464)